welcome to meditating with Chandra Vicki
I'm a cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientist at the University of
Toronto where academically and
scientifically studied mindfulness and
related phenomena eating like Insight
flow mystical experience transformative
experience higher states of
consciousness the cultivation of wisdom
and the aspiration to enlightenment
welcome I am also a practitioner I have
been practicing the past meditation that
a contemplation and touch each one for
over 29 years and teaching them for
close to 20 years this is a progressive
course every Monday as a Dharma day and
on that day I teach a new principle a
new practice to build on previous
principles and practices if you're
joining for the first time of course
you're welcome to stay but go to the
links in this description and that will
take you to previous lessons Tuesday
through Friday are sick days we meet
some tape sometimes I review what we did
on Dharma day Monday and then we sit
together at the end of every day there's
a Q&A I know some of you saw in a chat
that we might not be able to do Q&A
today because of some problems with Mars
internet but that's not the case mark
has been able to join us and we will be
able to take questions at the end I
would ask you if you can remember to
please like this video stream because
that will help raise its visibility on
the YouTube algorithm and that will help
me reach as many people as possible
with this these sets of practices that I
believe truly are very helpful to people
not only in general but in are
particularly pressing time all right
so I don't think there's anything else
like oh one more thing I did mention the
Q&A and we are going to be doing the
questions after all please limit those
questions at the end of today to the
meditation practice if you have more
general questions we do a live stream
every third Friday of the month
3 p.m. est okay I think that's
everything I've already reviewed the
number practice from Monday yesterday so
I think we're ready so please set your
phones right - do not disturb like get
yourself ready into your posture and we
will begin when I say begin begin
you
Shh slowly come out of your practice
trying as best you can to integrate what
you cultivate in your practice with your
everyday consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
so thanks to Amara we'll be able to take
some questions here and then Agustin
flies how to deal with them can I kill
them oh so that goes towards said that
the first promise so that's a difficult
question and I might struggle with some
of those questions I do change my diet
for example about Jason and myself we
don't eat mammals precisely because I
think they have a kind of life that they
find it haven't valuable to themselves
other people may be vegetarians or
vegans I don't want to specify a
particular place I don't think I have
the right to do that
I do you appreciate an honor that you
are reflecting on this question and the
promise and what it means to you I
suggest what I would what I do suggest
to you is that you read more deeply into
what enlightenment to build a consistent
ethical and moral practice there's some
good introductory talks to philosophical
works I think that's much more important
than me just stating what you should do
because that starts to shift it not to a
rule or command instead or continue do
what you're doing
my honor a deeply reflect on what this
means for you don't you don't just do
that in isolation read start to
cultivate what would it be like what do
you what can you do with genuine
conviction and consistency that's the
important thing about the integrity here
so that's how I would answer you I don't
have the authority to make moral
pronouncements I'm just your teacher ah
Tim Tim Dimitar I've been meditating on
and off for a year but I've been most
consistent since you started this course
thank you you're welcome
averaging
I think one hour per day these four
weeks how it takes me 30 to 40 minutes
video guided to reach the end of the
first quarter II by then my
concentration and low is just mental
endurance they've only done met at other
lessons of your time I don't feel like
I'm progressing but I have but I have
free time any suggestions yes try to I'm
not quite sure what standard you're
using so maybe relax the standard a
little bit about finding the core for
maybe as I said to the more light
version of finding your route you just
go through the set July and and go
through just here right this points in
the central line maybe in your flow
right you may be trying to get into a
very deep state of absorption and that
is again good but maybe again relax a
standard a little bit so just you know
and you know maybe spend them yourself
I'm going to spend maybe two three or
four breaths here here here my back get
into the flow I'm only going to count my
breaths
you know maybe three or four minutes you
don't want to get sort of set
it's called encoding specificity so that
there's always the expectation that it's
going to take that long to get into your
Center and Ruth
in fact what you're trying to do is
slowly gradually erode at how much time
it takes because if it's always taking
30 to 40 minutes then it's never going
to become second nature so you have to
try and trade a little bit you have to
you have to give up on getting quite so
deeply into those things so that you can
get in a little bit faster so that you
can move towards becoming second nature
so maybe shift your standard instead of
just depth of getting into the core for
it's all that you're not just trying to
get deeply in it in the meditation
you're trying to get into it deep enough
that deep enough in shorter and shorter
amounts of time so that it starts to
become progressively more second nature
to you perhaps reframing it that way
loosening the standards a little bit
shortening the time a little bit and
that's redirecting what you're trying to
do with the practice
gotcha help you want you want it to be
that you can just that's what it is a
martial arts in situation you can be
able to get like you're just into those
things like like that gonna be like
second nature eventually eventually
sorry I don't want to put any undue
pressure on anybody with that but slowly
slowly eroding the time like giving only
up a little bit on depth and then you'll
recover some of that depth as you do
more practice and you sort of dancing
your way towards taking not very much
time at all so Alexi siminoff but with
relaxing intensity we will not
compromise on zone of proximal
development by lowering the standard I
know because you know you're still
putting a demand on yourself right so
that's what I'm trying to say I'm trying
to get you that your question is helpful
thank you I'm trying to get you to keep
the demand but I'm trying to get you to
the demand to to distribute the demand
not only in terms of intensity but also
in to right trying to get to a place
where it's becoming more second nature
to you this is a more you're trying to
develop this into a like I said an
inhabited habit as a deep connection
between the words habit when originally
a cloak that the monk wore and
originally when you put the cloak on it
you know it's oh like think about like a
really woolen tunic and it's really
noticeable and it's great all right but
over time when you put on the cloak
eventually you put on the cloak and it
becomes second nature to you you become
habituated to it you inhabit it um
that's what well that's that's what I'm
trying to say you want to be in this
owner proximal development development
it has to be challenging but it needs to
be right your challenge isn't just how
intense the absorption is in in the in
the core floor but also longitudinally
and ice can i how much can i shorten
this and just give up a little bit on
the intensity and then stay there for a
bit and then can i shorten it and oh
you're right I'll lose a little bit of a
test
but I'll stay there better than the
intensity to come back eventually
eventually eventually eventually
eventually into the narrow account so
it's a bit of a dance and now that
you're moving into more fine-grain you
gotta like I say you got a Targa Lydia
Simon get ik Hermanson could you specify
again with countless thoughts to count
but did listening seen colours behind
your eyelids count yes anything that's
sort of coming up like that that's in
any way of seeing or a colour or a
sentence yes count it until you get as I
said something in which you're not
having any content of your experience
are there that perhaps that sort of
inner blackness but some people have for
a while and then that fades away to
remember though so your question is good
and I hope I've answered it but remember
don't get into an unnecessary sense of
demand of precision what was that what
thought or two or was that a thought
like if your initial intuition is it's a
thought and I'll count it they've
counted okay
the mad truth sometimes when I notice
and label the thought emotion or return
to breath I feel I'm ignoring
suppressing it and that this is not
healthy is this just my ego trying to
hold on to it or is it unhealthy um so
if I mean so there is a way of trying to
address your concerns I think it's a
real concern
have you tried meditating on your so
after you've noticed and labeled have
you done the practice of applying the
five factors of inquiry mindfulness to
the thought or emotion because that's a
way of not ignoring and suppressing it
allowing it to express itself but
turning it into transforming it into a
rena in which you are cultivating
mindfulness in the depths of those
automatic forms of you know a thought
that are happening pre usually
unconsciously for you i don't mean that
the thoughts are unconscious but the
process that generates them is
unconscious so one of the ways that's
one of the things about the
five factors of inquiring mindful my
distraction is it allows you to not
suppress or ignore but instead to
explore as a way of unpacking what's
there but but Trent but transforming it
into a friend an arena in which you are
cultivating a depth of mindfulness
inquiring mindfulness Rainer Ludwig what
is the difference between focus and
basic capacity when do you move from
full focus to the pasta so when you
found your focus you're basically doing
the pasta so when you have that you know
we've got that your focus here its focal
here and you have your all of your
peripheral awareness that field
awareness through your flow you're
actually now in doing the pasta so what
I say then you do the pasta what I mean
it's just keep doing what you've done
when you realize the core floor and
they're in process for you now at some
point you want to move like from basic
the pasta into deeper the pasta but
again I can't give you a win to that you
just sort that's more something you'll
get a sense of and it'll change as you
engage in the practice more
Simon get ik Hermanson could you get
John for me could you get to put on some
of the research regarding Cox I I'm
moving meditation I could use it from
education yes I'll try to do that I
apologize everyone I am for I am looking
at sitaji videos I'm looking at stuff
this is extremely busy time for me right
now just ending the January to April
term at U of T and I'm starting to
courses in summer terms which is
equivalent because it's condensed to
four courses so it's a very busy time
for me when things settle down a bit I
will get to doing a bit of that research
and also put up a list of things for
people but please be patient with me
that's going to take me a bit of time
Lynne Slater Harlan what to do on days
when the chatter in my
just won't stop I can't even hear myself
saying breath when I try to concentrate
on my breath yeah so those are very
difficult days you might try to switch
to Seoul in I think if I remember you
when you're in the wisdom saying I
taught you the walking meditation and so
when you when you're when it's just like
crazy like you're saying and I get that
and I know you're very honest with
yourself then try to move into a moving
mindfulness practice as your sole
practice for the day so if you don't
remember like I hope to be teaching you
guys that are very soon but then but if
you can remember it'll in I try to do
the the move like a moving mindfulness
practice like the walking meditation and
maybe if you remember any of that she
come or the each one that would be
helpful to be Athena I'm considering
acupuncture from some pain issues what
do you think about it um I think there's
good evidence that for many kinds of
issues disorders and diseases I'm doing
like this because I want to apply those
terms a little bit broadly than an
infection or braking which they tend to
be limited to in in Western medicine I'm
not a critic of Western medicine but I
think we want to expand well-being
beyond just being free of trauma
physical trauma and free of infection so
I think there's good evidence that
acupuncture can address a lot of these
issues especially issues that tend to
fall between the cracks what do I mean
by the issues that is hard to designate
as purely physical health issues or
mental health issues like chronic pain
right it seems to fall between those
acupuncture is very good for that I had
I did professional training in shiatsu
and I practiced it professionally for
over 10 years not because like I said
it's always important to do a meditative
hour a contemplative hour a movie
mindfulness art and if possible a
therapeutic healing mindfulness art and
there's deep connections between shiatsu
and acupuncture so I think within you
know a realm of reasonable plausibility
in terms of what there's empirical
research especially like I say that
stuff but that falls between the cracks
I think acupuncture is a good idea
Kyra Kroger I discovered body armor in
my right foot ankle it's associated with
an injury I've dealt with the trauma
around the injury in therapy but there's
still a lot of emotion emotion
associated with that how do i best
handle that so if you if you like within
clear honesty with yourself you think
you've dealt with the therapy because
I'm not giving you therapy here I want
to remind everybody died then I think
what you need to do is two things and
maybe alternate between them try session
where the emotion that comes up and
indirect matter towards that emotion you
just direct meta as if it was a person
you may even want to name it some people
name the emotion about the particular
emotion especially if it is familiar to
you notice the word familiar like a
family member and then direct method
towards it direct meta towards it and it
probably shifts around
listen but direct meta towards it and
then alternate that with unpacking it
with the five factors of inquiring
mindfulness and keep alternating between
those and and right and what will slowly
happen is you'll start it'll start to
articulate itself to you and you'll
start to enter into a dialogue with
those emotions and it will take time the
mat truth with general or past Noble
you're focusing on being in the body but
with deepening with past somebody seem
to be moving from the body and into the
mind is this not counter to our initial
purpose no because there's the deep the
deepening department is only one-half
and I'm going to show you next week of
what you're going to be putting into
with Praja there's a sense in which
you're trying to get sorry this will
sound metaphysical and sort of I hope
that doesn't want this pseudo Zen when
you do move to that space between your
thoughts there's a sense in which you're
moving beyond the mind and body together
but not in the sense of abandoning them
and getting into your head space but
they're always they that they're always
there is a foundation lifting you into
this place and then this is going to be
half of para and approach now the body
is going to be deeply deeply involved
again
so yeah you do want that the way I guess
I the body is present to me in that
depth is I go no I don't like using this
language because it sounds like somebody
who spent too much time in certain parts
of California but my body is present
even the depths of the pasta but not as
a spatial entity but as this energetic
ground the dynamic round that actually
makes my mind possible because that's
actually what your body is your lifts
body it's the dynamic ground of your
consciousness okay I hope that answered
everybody's questions and you know these
questions were so good today I just so
encouraging because the quality of these
questions I mean it means to me that I
think I'm teaching you and it's
working so I really appreciate this it's
very encouraging who can be helpful to
you I really want to thank everybody for
joining and I really want to thank my
good friend and techno major Mari was
behind the scenes dashing around trying
to make things work and as always like
some sort of you know quintessential
last-minute appearance of the superhero
he made I also wanted to thank Jason who
took over a lot of extra duties this
morning while Lamar was trying to get
back to us please like this video as I
mentioned it will raise the visibility
in the YouTube algorithm this whole
strip you do it like the whole screen
and that will help me reach more people
in connection with that please you know
share the this video series and these
practices with as many people as you
possibly can
and January I think it will be very
helpful in these difficult times please
subscribe to this channel to be notified
my video to receive notifications and
you'll also find lots of videos on my
channel within awakening the meaning
crisis and voices with rebecky about so
many of these topics that we talk about
in depth and put into a broader
framework and a broader context so
remember please we are doing this every
weekday morning at 9:30 est remember
continuity of practice is more important
than quantity of practice there is no
enemy worse than your own mind but there
is no ally no true friend greater than
your own mind take care everyone I'll
see you tomorrow